<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Propositions made by Monsieur Vander Hurst at the assembly of the Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces vpon the 13. of Ianuarie, 1608 With the answer of the sayd Generall States giuen vnto the sayd Monsieur Vander Hurst, touching the said propositions. And also a declaration made and sent by the said States Generall vnto all the prouinces and townes vnder their gouernment, touching peace to be made: printed 1608. The finall answer made by the said Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces vnto the Commissioners for the King of Spaine and the Archduke, assembled in the Hague, concerning peace to be made, 1608.</title>
            <title>Propositie vanden Heere vander Horst, ghedaen ende ghepresenteert ter vergaderinge vande ... Staten der Vereenighde Nederlanden den xiiien. Januarii 1607. English</title>
            <author>Wittenhorst, Walraven van, d. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120242</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855441</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855441</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20935</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15668)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20935)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 980:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Propositions made by Monsieur Vander Hurst at the assembly of the Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces vpon the 13. of Ianuarie, 1608 With the answer of the sayd Generall States giuen vnto the sayd Monsieur Vander Hurst, touching the said propositions. And also a declaration made and sent by the said States Generall vnto all the prouinces and townes vnder their gouernment, touching peace to be made: printed 1608. The finall answer made by the said Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces vnto the Commissioners for the King of Spaine and the Archduke, assembled in the Hague, concerning peace to be made, 1608.</title>
                  <title>Propositie vanden Heere vander Horst, ghedaen ende ghepresenteert ter vergaderinge vande ... Staten der Vereenighde Nederlanden den xiiien. Januarii 1607. English</title>
                  <author>Wittenhorst, Walraven van, d. 1623.</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Melchisidec Bradwood] for Philip Harison, and are to be sold at his shop in Corn-hill ouer-against the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Wittenhorst, Walraven van. Propositie vanden Heere vander Horst, ghedaen ende ghepresenteert ter vergaderinge vande .. Staten der Vereenighde Nederlanden den xiiien. Januarii 1607.</note>
                  <note>The speech was actually given in 1607; see Knuttel 1360, 1529a.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20935:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20935:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PROPOSITIONS MADE BY MONSIEVR VANDER HVRST AT THE Aſſembly of the Generall States of the <hi>Vnited Prouinces vpon the</hi> 13. <hi>of</hi> Ianuarie, 1608.</p>
            <p>WITH THE ANSWER OF THE ſayd Generall States giuen vnto the ſayd <hi>Monſieur Vander Hurst,</hi> touching the ſaid Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>And alſo A DECLARATION MADE AND SENT by the ſaid States Generall vnto all the Prouinces and Townes vnder their gouernment, touching Peace to be made: Printed 1608.</p>
            <p>The finall Anſwer made by the ſaid Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces vnto the Commiſſioners for the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> and the Archduke, aſſembled in the <hi>Hague,</hi> concerning Peace to be made, 1608.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Melchisedec Bradwood (McKerrow 380): "an owl, two snakes, and a rod"</figDesc>
               <head>M B</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Philip Hariſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Corn-hill ouer-againſt the Exchange. 1609.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="propositions">
            <pb facs="tcp:20935:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20935:2"/>
            <head>PROPOSITIONS Made by <hi>Monſieur <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ander Hurſt</hi> at the Aſſemblie of the Generall States <hi>of the Vnited Prouinces, vpon</hi> the 13. of Ianuarie, 1608.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>May it pleaſe you to be aduertiſed, that foraſmuch as that the high and mightie Princes, the Archduke <hi>Albertus</hi> and the Infanta <hi>Iſabella,</hi> haue long ſince had and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued great diſliking of and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the bloodie Netherland warres, as alſo of the great hurt, hinderance and vtter deſtruction, which the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof on both ſides do hereby endure and dayly fall into; and had rather ſee and behold the Netherlands (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought to a firme and moſt affured Peace) to reobtaine their ancient and priſtinate flouriſhing eſtate; haue not refrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both now and heeretofore to ſignifie vnto your Honors, not only by themſelues but by their meſſengers, what meanes they thought to be moſt fit to worke the ſame: as in May laſt they ſent me hither only to that end and purpoſe. But for that your Honours (in regard of the departure of Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> with ſome of your Honours Deputies from the <hi>Hague,</hi> about your martiall affaires) could not reſolue thereon, their High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20935:3"/>beare armes, and till this time to make and maintaine warre, haue not wiſhed nor craued more of God almightie (for the benefit, welfare, and ſecuritie of the ſayd Netherlands, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the good Inhabitants thereof) than to attaine vnto a godly, honourable, and an aſſured end of their ſayd warres, as they alſo with all their hearts at this preſent ſtill pray, deſire and beſeech God continually for the ſame. But for that by the ſayd Inſtruction dated in May aforeſayd (whereunto other Acts and Commiſſions haue a reference) it doth cleerely and euidently appeare, that their ſayd Highneſſe do as yet conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in their vngrounded pretence, that a certaine right and title doth yet belong and appertaine vnto them, to and in the ſayd Netherlands; whereas to the contrary the ſayd States doe euidently, plainly, and without contradiction maintaine and holde, That their ſayd Highneſſe neither can nor may by any meanes (otherwiſe than by force and power of warre) pretend any right or title vnto the Vnited Prouinces whatſoeuer: And that to the contrary, the ſayd Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces, vpon good and lawfull cauſes, haue alwayes eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and with vndoubted right vnderſtand, (for the vnion of the vnited Netherland Prouinces) That all the Prouinces, Townes, and Places, which for the maintenance of the ſayd vnion, haue by force, and otherwiſe ſecretly by practiſe beene taken and ſurprized, with violation of the ſolemne decree, are decreed and may be holden (by weightie and mightie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) for a free State. Which decree for the ſpace of ſeuen and twentie yeeres hitherwards, by diuers publike Acts and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and by the mightieſt Kings and Potentates of <hi>Europe</hi> hath beene confirmed, as alſo the ſayd States both for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and for all their deceaſed Adherents, (and as yet many thouſands Well-willers to the freedome of the Netherlands, ſighing vnder their Highneſſe gonernment, deſire to ſee a good end) by the ſpeciall grace of God, the aid and aſſiſtance of the aforeſayd Kings and Potentates, together with the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt meanes of the ſayd Prouinces, Quarters, Townes and Inhabitants, by a commendable right, haue hitherto maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20935:3"/>and are reſolued to maintaine and defend the ſame vnto the vttermoſt: and to that end the ſayd States vpon diuers the like offers and propoſitions (motioned not only by their ſayd Highneſſe and by the Emperours Maieſtie) haue declared, that it is neither godly, honourable, nor aſſured for them, to deale with thoſe who againſt the aforeſaid Decree holde and maintaine, and do inſiſt and alledge to haue right and title vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſayd vnited Prouinces. In the which Decree the ſayd States perſiſting, doe holde and account themſelues to be blameleſſe and innocent before God almightie and all the world, and ſpecially the Netherlands, of all the miſeries, hurts, and troubles happened vnto the ſayd Netherlands and their neighbours, by meanes of the ſayd vnlawfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and from the proceedings, which they the ſayd States for the maintenance of their ſayd right, haue beene conſtrained to take in hand. </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen in the <hi>Hague</hi> 
                  <date>the ſeuen and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of Ianuarie, 1608.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20935:4"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION made and ſent by the States <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall vnto all the Prouinces and Townes vnder their gouernment, touching the Peace to be made.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable and Worſhipful:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>for that the common cauſe of the vnited Prouinces, by Gods ſpeciall grace and fauour, is brought ſo farre, and to that end, that the Archdukes Highneſſe, in March laſt paſt by three ſeuerall motions in writing, haue thought good to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat and deſire vs, as with States of free Countries and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, wherunto their Highneſſe make no maner of pretence or title, to hearken vnto a treatie of peace, or truce, and abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from warres for many yeeres, with prouiſionall excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from beſieging and ſurprizing of Townes, and Forts, inuading or taking in of Prouinces and Quarters; as alſo of the making of new Forts, for the time of eight moneths next enſuing; that in the meane time, we may with them ſit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine vpon the ſaid Treatie, and to make an end of the ſaid Treatie before the firſt of September next comming: We with the aduice of his Eccellencie, and the Counſell of Eſtate, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thought and eſteemed it good, to accept and allow of the ſaid motion and prouiſionall exceptions, &amp; alſo to proceed to a further Treatie, &amp; thereof to giue our final reſolution before the firſt of September next enſuing, and herewith ſend letters of commiſſion to appeare, according to the contents of theſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20935:4"/>preſents. And although we are wel aſſured that your Honors and Worſhips are ſufficiently informed and certified of this motion and buſineſſe in hand, yet we thought it good to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe you thereof, and of our intents and purpoſes, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe and communicate the ſame, vnto and with the Kings of <hi>Great Britane, France,</hi> and <hi>Denmarke,</hi> as alſo with the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and other Townes of the Empire, with whom theſe Vnited Prouinces are in league and amitie; that hauing vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood their good intents, aduices, and counſels concerning theſe Vnited Prouinces, we may proceed to a farther and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per conſideration thereof heere in the ſaid Prouinces, and ſuch as ſhall be found meeteſt and beſt for the honor of God, the furthering of Chriſtian reformed religion, and the beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and moſt aſſurance of the ſame, and of the Vnited Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, and the Inhabitants thereof. And for that before all things, it is conuenient and neceſſarie that God Almightie ſhould with all our hearts be praiſed and thanked for his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and ſpeciall graces, ſhewed and beſtowed towards and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Countries, during theſe warres: and ſpecially, that it hath pleaſed him to mooue the hearts of the Archdukes, to make and motion the ſaid offers and propoſitions, as alſo to pray that it would pleaſe him, graciouſly to bleſſe the ſaid Treatie; that it may tend to the honor of his holie name, the maintenance and ſpreading abroad of his holie word; and of the Chriſtian reformed religion, together with the welfare and ſecuring of the Vnited Netherlands, and of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof: We haue thought it good, to ordaine and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, a generall Faſt, and day of prayer to be made and held in the Vnited Prouinces, vpon the 8. of Maie next enſuing: And therefore our deſire is, that your Honors ſhall cauſe the ſaid Faſting and Prayer day to be publiſhed and ploclaimed in al the places of the Prouinces of Holland and Weſt Freeſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, according to the accuſtomed maner therein vſed: and to command that the ſame may be holden and celebrated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, wherein you ſhall doe an acceptable peece of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, both vnto the Countrie and vs. Wherewith, Right
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20935:5"/>Honorable and Worſhipfull, and our ſpeciall good friends, we commit you to the protection of the Almighty.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated &amp;c.</dateline> and vnder written,
<signed>Iohn van olden Barnevelt.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>And lower there ſtood <signed>your ſpeciall good friends; the States Generall of the Vnited Prouinces of the Netherlands,</signed> and ſomewhat lower, <signed>by the ordinance of the ſayd States.</signed> Vnder written, <signed>C. Aerſous.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20935:5"/>
            <head>THE FINAL ANSWER made by the ſayd Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces, vnto the Commſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> and the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke, aſſembled in the <hi>Hague,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Peace to be made.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He States generall of the Vnited Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, hauing heard the report of their Deputies appointed to deale in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Peace, touching that which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the conference holden vpon the 20. of this moneth, by the Deputies for the High and Mightie King of Spaine, &amp;c. and for <hi>Albertus</hi> and <hi>Iſabella Clara ingenia,</hi> Archdukes of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, &amp;c. for the finall charge and commiſſion giuen them by the ſaid King and the Archdukes touching the generall points of the ſaid Treatie, vpon aduice of the Right Honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>William</hi> Earle of Naſſaue, &amp;c. and the Counſell of Eſtate of the ſayd Vnited Prouinces, for reſolution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, haue declared, and by theſe preſents doe declare, that the hurtfull fruits and iſſues of diuers fore-paſſed Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, during the Netherland warres, made with the King of Spaine laſt deceaſed, haue ſo much mooued the States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, for the ſpace of 25. yeeres together, both vpon the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers made in the behalfe of the ſaid King, his Gouernors and Succeſſours, as alſo at the motions and ſolicitations of the Emperours Maieſtie, together with the greateſt and chiefeſt Kings and Potentates of <hi>Europe,</hi> that they could not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to enter into, or hearken vnto any new treatie of Peace,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20935:6"/>but haue alwaies excuſed themſelues therein, fearing the like effects; ſo that alſo vpon the ſame Propoſitions made vnto them to the like end, in the moneth of Ianuarie 1607, in the behalfe of the high &amp; mightie Princes the Arch-dukes: they did roundly and by anſwer in writing declare, as alſo vnto the like propoſition not long before propounded by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors maieſty; the ſaid States made anſwer, that they thought it neither godly, honorable, nor ſecure, for them to enter into any treatie of Peace, with thoſe, that contrarie to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, maintained and eſtabliſhed, would ſeeme to oppoſe, or to iuſtifie themſelues to haue and pretend any title vnto the ſaid Countrie: and that withall, they did perſiſt, with prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation before God almightie, all the world, and ſpecially the Netherlands, to be blameleſſe and innocent of and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the miſeries, hurts and troubles which the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and their neighbours, together with the inhabitants thereof, by meanes of the aforeſaid vnlawfull pretences, haue ſuffered and indured, and yet were likely to ſuffer and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. Which anſwer being returned vnto the ſaid Archdukes, not long after ſeuerall letters and writings ſubſcribed with their hands, were by the ſaid Arch-dukes ſent vnto the ſaid Generall eſtates, whereby they ſignified vnto them, that they were content to deale with them as with States of a free Countrey, (and for the which they ſo held and accounted both them and it, and whereunto they made not any pretence) touching a perpetuall Peace, or a truce and abſtinance from warres, for many yeeres. And in the firſt of the aforeſaid Acts it was ſaid, that by the making of a Truce euery man ſhould hold that which he held and poſſeſſed; and by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of a Peace, that which ſhould be agreed vpon; as alſo that the Vnited Prouinces ſhould deſiſt and abſtaine from trafficking vnto the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, &amp;c. Whereunto the ſaid States roundly made refuſall; which the ſaid Arch-dukes perceiuing, made anſwer, that they were content that euery man both by Truce and Peace ſhould poſſeſſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy that which he held, and claimed to bee his owne, vnleſſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20935:6"/>that by exchange of any places by common conſent, they could otherwiſe agree: and at the ſame time alſo the clauſe of defiſting from trafficking and ſailing vnto the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, was omitted, according to their Act to that end made, bearing date the 13. of March, in the aforeſaid yeere. Vpon the which Act the 12. of Aprill, after certaine points touching the nomination of their reſpectiues Committies, being agreed vpon betweene the Deputies for the ſaid Arch-dukes, and the Generall States, vpon the foure &amp; twentieth of the ſame moneth, by a formall inſtrument vnder written by their ſaid Highneſſe, and ſealed with their great ſeales, and with their accuſtomed ſignatures and Paraphraſes: and an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writing likewiſe ſealed, Paraphraſed, and vnder-written, in the behalfe of the Generall States, in qualitie as States of free Countries and Prouinces; whereunto the Arch-dukes did not pretend any right or title, it was agreed, and by their ſaid Highneſſe promiſed, to hold and obſerue, and to cauſe to be holden and obſerued the aforeſaid declaration made vnto the ſaid Generall States, and to make reſtitution, and cauſe the ſame to be made for all direct and indirect courſes taken and vſed contrarie vnto the ſame, and beſides thoſe let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of confirmation, to cauſe the like declaration to bee ſent from the King of Spaine (for as much as it concerned him) vnto the ſaid Generall States, within three moneths then next enſuing, with all generall and particular renouncings, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances thereunto belonging. And thereupon the Truce for abſtaining from all acts of hoſtilitie being alſo agreed vpon: There were three acts of confirmation and conſent ſent into <hi>Holland</hi> from the ſaid king; two of them bearing date the laſt of Ianuarie; and one the eighteenth of March, in the yeere aforeſaid: the laſt of them containing theſe words in effect. And for that the aforeſaid Arch-duke our brother, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to make the ſaid Treatie, and thereupon to deliuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid States, our letters of ratification, and the like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, with all generall and particular renuntiations, and promiſes, as the cauſe requireth: Wee vpon ripe deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20935:7"/>and aduice, vpon our certaine knowledge, and abſolute kingly power, for the holding and performing of the ſaid promiſe, and the aſſuring of the principall Treatie of Peace, or of a long Truce to be made: doe by theſe preſents make the like declaration vnto the States aforeſaid, that our brother hath made, whereof mention is before made, foraſmuch as the ſame concerneth vs: And ſpecially we declare, that wee are well pleaſed and contented, that in our owne name, and in our behalfe, a Treatie ſhall be made with the ſaid States, in qualitie, and as eſteeming and holding them for free Countries, Prouinces and States; whereunto wee make no pretence of Soueraigntie: and alſo haue approoued, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ratified, and by theſe preſents doe approoue, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and ratifie, all and euerie one of the points, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and contained in the ſaid Treatie: and promiſe by the word of a king to hold and obſerue them all, and to cauſe them to be held and obſerued as wholly and particularly, as if we had at the beginning thereof declared, conſented and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the ſame, and as if they had beene proceeded in, and concluded by our conſent and authoritie, and will not do, nor cauſe any thing to be done contrarie vnto the ſame: and alſo will promiſe to recompence and make amends for all direct or indirect courſes vſed and taken contrarie vnto the ſame, in ſuch maner that all the aforeſaid points ſhall be truely obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, holden, and fulfilled vnto and with the ſaid States: Whereunto we binde our ſelues by the word of a Prince, with all the generall and particular renuntiations and obligations thereunto requiſite and needfull. We alſo promiſe, that as ſoon as the Treatie of Peace, or long Truce, ſhalbe concluded and agreed vpon, that wee will cauſe all diſpatches neceſſarie to be made for the fulfilling and execution of that which ſhall be capitulated and agreed vpon, in good maner and forme, as they ought to be: ſo that in all things, and thorowout all the foreſaid Vnited Prouinces, whole and full ſatisfaction ſhalbe made touching the aforeſaid promiſe &amp; confirmation, and with expreſſe reiection of all that which may be contrarie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20935:7"/>or againſt the ſaid confirmation: and withall, expreſly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that the Generall States, as States of free Countries, whereunto the King and the Arch-dukes make no pretence of Soueraigntie, by the grace of God Almightie, and the aide of their allies (nominating the Kings of <hi>Great Britaine, France, Denmarke,</hi> and other Potentates) which in the ſaid Prouinces ſhal and may take order and maintaine all cauſes that concerne the welfare of the State and gouernment (amongſt the which, before all, the point of Religion is to be maintained, and the ſame expreſly giuen in charge vnto the Arch-dukes Deputies) concerning the ſaid Prouinces, and the good Inhabitants thereof: ſo that in the chiefe Treatie, nothing ſhall or may be propounded againſt the ſame; (vnleſſe that men ſhould ſeeke to preuent and contrarie the aforeſaid formall and ſolemne promiſe.) Laſtly it was concluded by the Generall States, that the Deputies of the ſaid King and the Arch-dukes, might come vnto the <hi>Hague,</hi> there to intreat and agree vpon the ſaid Treatie, with full information, charge, and authoritie to ſhew their meanings plainly and ſincerely therein: as alſo to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the States intent and meaning, that ſo they might make a ſhort and breefe reſolution therein.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Deputies being come vnto the <hi>Hague,</hi> and hauing entred into Treatie with the Deputies of the ſaid States, at the beginning there was a new cleere and expreſſe promiſe and ratification made, not onely to the ſaide States, but alſo vnto all the particular Prouinces, and Lordſhips, thereunto depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as alſo vnto the Quarters, Lordſhips, Townes and Places of other Prouinces holden by the ſaid States, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the foreſaid promiſes, dated the 24. of Aprill, both in the name of the King of Spaine, and the Arch-dukes, being procured and to be procured from them, and all and euerie one of their heires and ſucceſſors, in their Kingdomes, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and States, decreeing and declaring that they pretend not any title in or vnto the aforeſaid Vnited Prouinces, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, Lands, Townes and Places, as then holden and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the ſaid States, and that they held and accounted them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20935:8"/>for free States, Prouinces, Lordſhips, Countries, Townes and Places, with promiſe vpon their words and honours, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the words of Princes, not to doe any thing contrary vnto the ſame, nor permit it to be done, (no not in vſing the names, titles, or armes of the ſaid Prouinces, or otherwiſe) directly or indirectly in any wiſe whatſoeuer: as alſo that from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, at all times and for euer, there ſhould be a good, firme, indiſſoluble Peace betweene the aforeſaid high and mightie King and the Archdukes their children, and ſucceſſors, and the aforeſayd States, in the qualitie aforeſayd, for all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Lands, Lordſhips, Townes and Places which the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd Kings, Archdukes, and States held and poſſeſſed, with their reſpectiue ſubiects and inhabitants, which reſide therein at this time, or that heereafter ſhall dwell therein, without exception of any man whatſoeuer. Alſo, that the ſayd King and Archdukes, and the ſayd States, in qualitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, together with their reſpectiue ſubiects and inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants ſhould from thencefoorth liue in good friendſhip, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vſing any more hoſtilitie, with forgetting of all forepaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed cauſes and actions. But in the proceſſe of the Treatie, the Deputies in the behalfe of the ſaid King and Arch-dukes, ſought to abridge and diminiſh the aforeſaid acknowledged freedome of the Vnited Prouinces, in the principalleſt point thereof, and to make it of no effect, as amongſt the reſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly in the generall trafficke and nauigation, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences thereof, wherein the chiefe and principall welfare of the aforeſaid Prouinces conſiſteth. Alſo, in the pretences (onely to the euident and manifeſt ouerthrow of the Vnited Prouinces, without cauſe or reaſon) of diſmembring ſome of the vnited Prouinces of that which without deniall (according to the agreement made) belonged vnto them. Alſo in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation touching the freedome and ſoueraigntie of certaine Townes, held and poſſeſſed by the States, as alſo of the Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges appointed for places of receit and accounts, in demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of certaine lands, which by former Princes had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, and otherwiſe, coucrtly ſpeaking of the point-of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20935:8"/>without making any free or open propoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion thereof: and being vrged to ſpeake their mindes freely and fully there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſometime they ſaid, that they would not doe any thing contrarie to the freedome and ſoueraigntie (to the diſlike or diſcontentment of the States of the vnited Prouinces) touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the point of Religion; and yet at another time, they ſaid they muſt conſult with them of Spaine touching the point of Religion, and that touching the ſame, and concerning the point of generall trafficke and nauigation, ſome of them muſt expreſly goe into Spaine. And although that the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid States Generall, perceiuing the ſaid proceedings might well haue broken vp the ſaid Treatie, notwithſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the great importance thereof, and deſiring for their parts before God, and before all Kings, Potentates, Princes, and Common-wealths of Europe, and ſpecially before the Commons of the vnited Prouinces, to make knowne, that they with all their hearts, and vprightly deſire to alter and change the long, hurtfull, and bloodie warres of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, into a godly, honorable, and an aſſured peace, for the comfort and vnburthening not onely of the Inhabitants of the Netherlands, but alſo of the neighbour countries and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; thought good by the aduice and good counſell of the Ambaſſadors of the Kings of <hi>Great Britaine, France, Denmarke,</hi> &amp;c. and of the Euangelicall Electors and Princes of Germanie (who at their earneſt requeſts, were ſent vnto the Netherlands, to aide and aſſiſt them in the ſaid Treatie and buſineſſe of ſo great importance) that one of the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the King and the Arch-dukes, ſhould goe into Spaine, to vnderſtand the Kings abſolute intent and meaning, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it was expreſly ſignified and declared by the States, that they would not conſent vnto the like delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but onely for that time, and that the ſaid Deputie ſhould expreſly returne againe with the ſaid reſolution, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two moneths then next after enſuing. And to that end the Truce for the moneths of Aprill and May was continued and prolonged. After that by meanes of the long ſtaying of him
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20935:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20935:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:20935:10"/>that was ſent into Spayne, before the end of the moneth of May, the aforeſaid Truce by common conſent, was prolong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vntill the laſt of December laſt paſt: but the States once again and plainly told the Deputies for the ſaid King and the Arch-dukes, that their meaning was, within two moneths at the fartheſt, after the moneth of May, they would haue a finall end and breaking vp of the ſaid Treatie. Whereupon as in the beginning of the moneth of Iune, and after from time to time, diuers letters and aduices were brought and came from ſeuerall Countries and Kingdomes, that the ſaid king of Spaine and the Spaniſh Counſell did not proceed tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vprightly in the ſaid Treatie, but by delaies and all the meanes they could, ſought to vndermine the State of the vnited Prouinces: Preſently thereupon, as about the middle of Iune, the ſaid Deputies for the King and the Arch-dukes were aduertiſed by the Generall States of the ſaid aduice ſent them, with earneſt requeſt by them made, to vnderſtand and know their vttermoſt intent and meaning: and withall it being told them, that notwithſtanding the Truce was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed and continued for the whole yeere, yet it was the States meaning, not to ſuffer the delay of the end of the ſayd Treatie any longer than vntill the laſt of Iuly, and that they might then preſently breake vp and depart, if their intents were not to bring the Treaty to any good end: Wherupon the ſayd Deputies made anſwer, That they held thoſe aduices to be wholly vntrue, and that they were otherwiſe fully certified and aſſured, after that ſome few dayes, before the expiration of the moneth of Iuly, certifying the States, that they had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that the Commiſſarie generall was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to attend at the Court vpon the fifteenth of Iuly, to receiue his diſpatch, and that without doubt hee would be there very ſhortly: whereupon the matter being conſidered of, vntill the twentieth of Auguſt, and in the meane time newes of the continuance of the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> intent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from all places, it was thought good the ſame day to haue another conference with the ſayd Deputies, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20935:10"/>their vttermoſt authoritie and meanings: who at the ſame time declared, That the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> and the Arch-dukes reſolute intents were, that the agreement made ſhould be obſerued and kept, and that the vnited Prouinces by their ſayd acknowledgement and agreement ſhould be free and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne countreys, without pretence of any right, vaſſallage, or other ſouereignty to be ſought or pretended by them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in or thereunto, vpon condition that in regard thereof, the Romiſh Catholike religion ſhould be reeſtabliſhed in the ſayd Prouinces; and that the ſubiects and inhabitants of the ſayd Prouinces ſhould preſently and from that time forth leaue off and deſiſt from trade, traffike, and nauigation into <hi>India;</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring alſo, that they ſtill perſiſted in the difficulties touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the raiſing of conuoyes, the diſmembring of the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Gelder,</hi> touching all the high quarter thereof, the holding of the places vpon and being on the other ſide of the <hi>Reyn,</hi> as alſo vpon the borders of the Empire, which without all controuerſie are neutrall Townes, belonging to the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the Empire, as alſo touching the pretence of villages and the head banks or chambers of accounts in Townes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto the States in other Prouinces; alſo that the Arch-dukes ought to enioy the lands belonging vnto the Princes of the houſes of <hi>Burgondie</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> being Lords in the time of the reſpectiue vnited Prouinces. And for that the moſt part of the aforeſayd points can not be holden nor eſteemed, but as pretences againſt the decreed, maintained, confirmed and confeſſed freedome of the vnited Prouinces, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, openly repugning againſt the ſayd Treatie and the confirmation thereof, and withall againſt the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle that is thereby agreed vpon: therefore the States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the vnited Prouinces vnderſtand, that they for the ſtate of the ſayd countreys, and of the good inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, can not finde it good to enter into any further Treatie with the ſayd Deputies, being heartily ſory, that contrary to their intents, the ſayd Treatie hath been ſo vnprofitably broken off, neuertheleſſe contenting themſelues, that they, before God
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20935:11"/>and all the world, may be held inculpable, that the bloodie and long continued warres of the Netherlands are not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into a Chriſtian, honourable, and an aſſured peace, and a finall end made and procured of all the calamities, miſeries, hurts, and hinderances which the ſayd Netherlands, and their neighbors, together with the good inhabitants of the ſame haue endured, and are like to endure, by meanes of the vnlawfull pretences of their aduerſe parties.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Done in the <hi>Hague</hi> in full aſſemblie of the Generall States of the vnited Prouinces, &amp;c.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="printers_device">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device (McKerrow 306): "Framed device of Truth attacked by Calumny and upheld by Time"</figDesc>
                  <head>VERITAS FILIA TEMPORIS</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20935:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
